Trevor Olsen

Sr Data Scientist

Contact: (651) 226-1149 | Alexandria, VA

Email: tvolsenmath@gmail.com Website: https://tvolsen.github.io/

LinkedIn: https://linkedin.com/in/tvolsen1/

Summary: Double Ph.D. in Computer Science and Mathematics with 3 years of experience in the finance industry developing machine learning models and data-pipelines to operate at scale. In my current role I am focused on improving price predictions and ranking comparable sales for homes across the United States. I have an extensive background in academia, which includes coursework in machine learning, deep learning, statistics, linear algebra and graph theory as well as 7 publications in the fields of robotics, discrete mathematics and statistics.

WORK HISTORY

Senior Data Scientist, Freddie Mac

08/2022 - Present

- **Our House Price Prediction Model Enhancement:**
 - ➤ Created a house price prediction deep learning model which covers 100 million properties in the US. Provided a 2% accuracy boost compared to production in pre-defined testing regions
 - > Implemented a constant time geospatial lookup algorithm to enable enhanced data engineering
 - Developed a pipeline that unified 5+ vendor data sources, improving data coverage and runtime

Comparable Sales Model:

- ➤ Proposed and constructed tree-based appraiser adjustment models which are within 5% of the actual appraiser adjustment in 99% of the validation set
- ➤ Initiated and built a comparable sales recommendation system to generate a ranking of the best comparable sales for new construction homes. This doubled the coverage on new construction homes with an identical performance to production model
- o Team Leadership and Collaboration:
 - ➤ Planned and organized the 2024 Q3 hackathon to enrich the geospatial data for production models. New features provided a 1-2% boost in production price prediction models over initial testing regions
 - Was selected as an officer to oversee the comparable sales model initiative
 - ➤ Won the 2023 Q1 Hackathon which involved matching school boundaries to US properties by developing the algorithm that had the best coverage and fastest runtime
 - > Developed automation scripts to assist new hires through the onboarding process
- **Lecturer**, University of South Carolina

08/2016 - 12/2021

- o Taught 18 courses including: statistics, linear algebra, multivariate calculus and advanced algorithms
- O Earned an average student evaluation of 4.75/5
- **Adjunct Faculty**, Miami Dade College

05/2015 - 08/2016

- o Instructed a wide range of classes including: statistics, calculus and financial mathematics
- o Average student evaluation of 4.9/5

EDUCATION

• **Ph.D. in Computer Science**, University of South Carolina

01/2022

- O Developed more than 5 sampling methods which reduced the runtime by 90% when compared to the best know algorithm and solved novel problems in the robotics pursuit-evasion domain. This code was implemented in C++ with additional Python and Shell scripts to automate over 5000 simulations. This resulted in 3 publications with 2 additional papers in preparation
- **Ph.D. in Mathematics**, University of South Carolina

05/2020

O Analyzed over a billion graph isomorphism classes and generalized structures by density-based invariants. Code was written in Python (SageMath) and resulted in 3 publications with 2 more in preparation

• M.A. in Mathematics, University of Miami

05/2015

• **B.S. in Computer Science and Math**, Palm Beach Atlantic University

05/2013

• **Coursework:** Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Advanced Statistics and Probability, Regression Analysis, Robotics, Parallel Computing, Image Processing, Linear Algebra, Graph Theory, Advanced Algorithms

COMPETENCIES

- Programming Experience Python (PyTorch, Scikit-learn, Tensorflow, Pandas, Numpy, Jupyter, NetworkX), SQL, C++, R
- **Theory** Deep Learning, Machine Learning, Large Language Models (LLM), Natural Language Processing (NLP), Graph Neural Networks, Statistics, Robotics, Linear Algebra
- **Personal Interests** Video/board games, foster failure dog dad, hiking, college football, woodworking

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS & PERSONAL PROJECTS

- Robust-by-Design Plans for Multi-Robot Pursuit-Evasion
 - Utilized intelligent sampling method and an enhanced DFS to effectively create a plan to pursue and evader, regardless of robotic failures
 - O International Conference on Robotics and Automation (2022)
- Minimum Wiener Index of Triangulations and Quadrangulations
 - o Found the structure which minimizes the Wiener Index on maximally planar graphs and a closed formula for this index as a function of the number of vertices, results were proven to be optimal
 - o Discrete Applied Mathematics (2022)
- Clinical Characteristics of Suspected COVID-19 in Pediatric Patients
 - o Conducted statistical analysis on study comparing positive and negative COVID-19 patients
 - o International Journal of Critical Care and Emergency Medicine (2021)
- NCAA March Madness Bracket Predictor
 - o Assembled 20 years of data with web scraping before pre-processing
 - o Predicted the correct winner with 75% accuracy using predictive models
 - Utilized a Bayesian optimizer to tune the hyper-parameters